Finding Aid to the Healing Alternatives Foundation Records, 1986-1994
UCSF Library and Center for Knowledge Management, Archives and Special Collections
Healing Alternatives Foundation records
1986-1994
MSS 94-55
Healing Alternatives Foundation Records
Number of containers: 1 box Linear feet: .3
The UCSF Library and Center for Knowledge Management, Archives and Special Collections University of California, San Francisco 530 Parnassus Avenue San Francisco, CA 94143-0840 Phone: (415) 476-8112 Fax: (415) 476-4653 Email: http://www.library.ucsf.edu/collres/archives/contactform.html URL: http://www.library.ucsf.edu/collres/archives/
Records of the Healing Alternatives Foundation, including meeting minutes, correspondence, planning documents, publicity, newsletters, design/artwork files, funding sources and strategies.
Information for Researchers
Access
Collection is open for research.
Alternate Forms Available
There are no alternate forms of this collection.
Related Collections
Guerilla Clinic Records, MSS 90-12
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
AIDS (Disease)--United States--History; Community Foundations; AIDS activists--United States; Healing Alternatives Foundation
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
The Healing Alternatives Foundation Records were donated to the UCSF Library 1994.
System of Arrangement
Arranged to the folder level.
Organizational History
Healing Alternatives Foundation (HAF) was formed as a "buyer's club" in April of 1987 in direct response to the need for access to treatment information and products. It was founded with the belief that HIV/AIDS can be a treatable, chronic disease requiring both early preventative measures and aggressive treatment of opportunistic infections. That philosophy is accompanied by the conviction that people with HIV should become informed about and involved with their own program of treatment and that treatment options should be both available and affordable.
By pooling resources, founders were able to develop direct services to people with AIDS, who join HAF in order to purchase materials at bulk prices. By 1993, membership was around 6,000 and was growing steadily. Members come to HAF for information about treatments, access to various low-cost products, and the opportunity to share with other members. HAF also maintains an extensive library on HIV, human immunity, and alternative healing practices and therapeutics.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection documents both this particular organization and the phenomena of buyer's clubs, which have been a major source of unapproved medications and other treatment modalities since the mid-1980s. Among the documents in the first folder of the collection is one from 1986 titled "Federally Unapproved Medications for the Treatment of AIDS and ARC; How to Get Them, How to Bring Them Home, and How to Use Them." This is an overview of how these substances were originally obtained, with a description of how to buy drugs in Mexico and deal with border crossings ("...look as ordinary as possible; consider it a new type of drag").
The folder titled "Photographs" contains eight snapshots of unidentified HAF members from about 1986 displaying products recently obtained on a run to Mexico. The folder labeled "FDA and 1992 ddC Incident" contains documentation of a 1992 FDA sampling and testing of ddC tablets purchased from HAF. These document a particular investigation and HAF's response to it, but they also reveal the attitude and approach of the FDA and its relationship with buyer's clubs in general. The final two folders indicate the range of products available in 1992 and how particular products were ordered.
Container List
- Description and History, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Articles & Bylaws, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Board of Directors: Lists, Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Board Minutes, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Board Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Board Minutes, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Board Minutes, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Operations Committee, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Staff: Policies, Procedures, Memos, etc, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Board & Staff Retreat, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Newsletter, 1998; 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Publicity, Press Releases, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Volunteer Program, Memos, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Annual Reports, 1987; 1988,; 1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Reports, Miscellaneous, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "HAF Gets Aggressive", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Library Development, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "Transition '92", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- National Buyers Club, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Passive Immunotherapy Foundation; Correspondence, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Local Independent Agencies and Combined Charities, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- FDA and 1992 ddC Incident (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Ordering, Product Notes, Price List, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Inventory, March, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)